<resources>
    <string name="app_name">A Thousand Beginnings and Endings</string>
    <string name="forbidden_fruit_story">Do not trust the fruit of Maria Makiling.\nIf you find your pockets full of thorny fruit, throw it out the window.\nDo not taste it. Do not stroke the rind and wonder at the impossible pink\nof its color . . . not meat pink or tongue pink, but that delicate rose of\ndawn pushing herself from the arms of night. It is not a color of this\nworld.\nFill your pockets with salt. Turn your shirt inside out. Tell Maria you\nhave taken nothing.\nBut when you walk away, say a prayer.\nFor it is not her fault.\nThe Mountain couldn’t help but stare.\nShe had been staring since the moon was nothing but a knob of\nunripe fruit, and she had been leaning out over her palace since the sky\nwas still the raw and wounded red of a newborn.\nMortals were not beautiful in the sense that their features were\npleasing, although some of them had pleasing features, of course. But in\ntruth, they were beautiful because you could only glimpse them. They\nwere beautiful for their fragility, disappearing as fast as a bloom of ice\nbeneath sunlight. And made more beautiful by the fact that they were\nalways changing.\n“Dayang,” said her father, peering down from his clouds. “Be careful\nnot to lean out so far that your heart falls out.”\nThe Mountain merely laughed.\nHer heart was safe.\nIt was an ill-fated thing to claim that a heart is safe. Hearts are\nrebellious. The moment they feel trapped, they will strain against their\nbindings.\nAnd it was so with the Mountain.\nFew visited her, for few could climb the sides of the Mountain. In\nthis way, the Mountain diwata discovered loneliness. It was the feeling\nof negative space, the sudden cold of a column of sunlight moving\nslowly elsewhere. The diwata wondered what it would be like to be held\nby the same set of arms each day and night. The Mountain shed lovers\nlike seasons. It was the diwatas’ way, just as fruit could not help but fall,\nand rain could not help but slide.\nOne day, the diwata went near the bottom of her slope and bathed in\na small pool there. When she finished, she let her black hair dry on a\nsun-warmed rock. Her eyes closed.\nShe waved her hands lazily, sleepily. Beneath her palms, a cluster of\nanemones unfurled from the ground and nuzzled her fingers. A face rose\nto mind: a human boy with sloe eyes who had wandered up the Mountain\na few days past. He had not seen her, which had not surprised her. But\nwhat had surprised her was the flare of disappointment in her heart. She\nwanted to be seen.\nA quiet snap broke her thoughts.\nA different silence chased the stillness. It was not the silence of\nemptiness, but intention. It felt like a living thing.\nSomeone had meant to stop.\nThe Mountain jolted upright.\nThere, standing in the clearing of the woods, was a young mortal\nman. He wore a beautiful hunting cloak and held a knife, but when he\nsaw her, he dropped it. He sank to his knees, flinging out his arms.\n“Goddess, I beg your forgiveness,” said the young man.\nThe Mountain held back a snort. It was not kind to laugh in the face\nof faith. Yet she was still young, too, and had not learned how to mask\nher features. Around her, the wind crinkled the leaves.\nThe young man looked up from his prostration.\n“I am no goddess,” said the Mountain.\nHis eyebrows curved into a question. “Are you not the spirit of the\nMountain?”\n“I am.”\nBut she thought of her mother, her sisters—the ones who spent their\ntime painting stars onto the sky, swelling rivers, and dreaming of new\nbeings. Not like her, whose duty was to tend and not create. Not that the\nMountain minded. She got to be close to something that was just a\ndistant dream to the others. She got to be near humans.\nThe man stood. The Mountain stared. His eyes were not yet crimped\nby too much sun. His hair was raven lustrous and his muscles lean and\nsleek. Her heart, though still firmly behind her bones, leaned out\ncuriously.\n“Then forgive my presumption,” he said. “I couldn’t help but think\nthat the most beautiful woman I had ever seen would naturally be a\ngoddess.”\nShe pushed herself off the rock and walked toward him. His eyes\nwidened, wonder tilting his brows and parting his lips. A thrill ran\nthrough the Mountain. She laced frost in her hair like a bejeweled net to\ngather the black strands and expose the steep drop of her neck. Her dress\nshone sheer and iridescent, crafted of a thousand beetle wings and shells\npolished to the point of translucence. When she touched him, he\nshuddered. She wanted to put her lips at his neck’s pulse point, to sip\nlightly at all the things that made him human.\n“I would have you,” she said simply.\nThe man’s eyes widened. And the Mountain, though she could\nneither bend nor break, felt her landscape ripple beneath that gaze. He\nwas the first human to see her. It was one thing to crouch unseen and stay\nseparate. It was quite another to stand beheld.\nShe reached for him, and he reached back.\nThe Mountain had loved and been loved by many. But none had been\nhuman.\nIt was different. His blood ran hot beneath his skin. There was\nurgency here  .  .  . and the Mountain wondered distractedly whether it\nmight scorch her.\nImmortals have no urgency. There was never any rush. All\nlovemaking was slow as poured honey.\nThis was not.\nAnd the Mountain rather liked it.\n“What is your name?” she asked, when they lay still on a bed of\nanemones.\n“Bulan,” he said.\nLanguage was not yet pleated into symbols. She could not trace his\nname upon his chest. Instead, she sounded out the name against his wrist,\nbeneath his ear, upon his neck.\n“And yours?” he asked, propping himself on his elbow.\nHe looked at her, and the Mountain tried to think of what his eyes\nlooked like. They were dark. Shining. Like the black glass left over when\na volcano spends its fury.\n“You may call me Dayang.”\nPrincess.\nBulan smiled. “A fitting name.”\nThe village worried for Bulan. When he did not return from his hunting\nexpedition by nightfall, search parties combed the forest. At the bottom\nof Mount Makiling, they found him. He was grinning, arms laden with\nfruits and vegetables.\n“I must have lost track of time,” he said.\nThe villagers were too relieved to notice how he grinned wistfully,\nturning his head over his shoulder, as if he had forgotten something\nprecious on the mountainside.\nFrom that day on, Bulan spent less and less time in the village. He\ndid not allow anyone to join him on his expeditions through Mount\nMakiling. “Too dangerous,” he said. But there was a possessive edge to\nhis voice.\nEvery night, Bulan would return with the creamiest nuts, berries that\nheaved with juice, fruits that dreamed of flying and not falling, and so\narched their green necks to the sun to become all the sweeter for their\ndreaming. The villagers, though grateful, could not help but wonder\nwhere Bulan spent so much of his time. The Mountain was all that\nseparated them from other villages—villages whose chiefs might have\nwondered over the riches on the other side of the mist, or seafaring\nqueens who might have speculated on the plumpness of the fish just\naround the Mountain’s curves. Bulan’s village might know peace, but it\nhad not forgotten wariness. Though a few young men had tried to follow\nBulan into the Mountain, a blanket of fog and mist always curtained him\nfrom sight. As if the Mountain was keeping him all to itself.\nBut Bulan did not just receive.\nHe gave, too.\nHe brought the Mountain a feather so white it rivaled pearls and\nthreaded it through her hair. He brought a perfectly spiraled shell with a\nsea’s stolen reverie floating in its echo.\n“I feel rather like an infant,” said Bulan one day, laughing. “I bring\nyou useless, shiny things, for what else could I give someone like you?”\nBy now, some months had passed. The Mountain enjoyed his\ncompany. Not just the touch of his hands and his skin against hers, but\nhis conversation. His dreams. He was no longer merely something that\nintrigued. He was no longer a thing to her at all. When he left, her heart\nstrained hard against her chest, as if it might chase after him. And when\nhe returned, her smile sent a tremor through the world. More and more,\nshe found herself searching for the jewel-bright line of his hunting cloak\namong the leaves. She looked for him when he wasn’t there, and reached\nfor him when he was, and in that way the Mountain found herself part of\na rhythm that she had, for once, created. It seemed like an act of the\ngods. To love.\nSo when he asked what he might give her, her answer fell bluntly\nfrom her lips:\n“Your heart.”\nHer answer was met with silence. Bulan watched her, weighing\nsomething secret behind his eyes, and said nothing. He kissed her lightly.\n“I will be back.”\nThe Mountain stared after him. She thought he might not return, but\nthe next day, he stood before her. A delicate feather strung round with\nbeads hung from his hand. Folded under his arm was a rough-spun linen\ndress and a small bundle. He looked as if he had not slept.\nWhen she approached, he prostrated himself once more upon the\nground.\n“Dayang,” he said. “You always had my heart. But I would give you\nmore than that, if you would permit me. I would offer my hand in\nmarriage, my hearth and home, my humble bed and humbler roof.”\nIt had not occurred to the Mountain that Bulan might want things,\ntoo. And to realize that he returned her affections sparked a great deal of\njoy in the Mountain.\nShe wore the dress for Bulan, even though the thread sliced at her\nskin and the wooden sandals pinched her toes and the pearl comb tugged\nher scalp. She tried her best to fit in the clothes. And when he\npronounced her maganda—“beautiful,” a meaningless word made golden\nby the alchemy of his lips—she smiled. She wore his promise around her\nneck.\nThat night, when they made love, she leaned over him. Her hair\nbrushed against his face. The tip of her feather necklace trailed his chest.\nShe leaned so far her heart fell out.\nAnd she didn’t even notice.\nWhen Bulan gathered her to him, he noticed something in his hand. A\ngem no larger than his thumbnail.\n“Dayang,” he said.\nIt still meant “princess,” but it no longer seemed formal. It had no\nheft, only the worn softness of familiarity.\n“What is this?” he asked. “Is it yours?”\nThe Mountain looked at it for a long while.\nBeings like her do not need hearts. They live without them with ease.\nA heart is important only to those who want to leave the place that\ntethers their souls and gives them form. And the Mountain, staring into\nthe openness of Bulan’s face, had no desire to leave.\n“It is my heart,” she said. She folded his fingers over the gem. “You\nwill be my husband, and so your heart is mine. And I shall be your wife,\nand so my heart is yours. Guard it well.”\nThe Mountain and Bulan decided that she would come down from the\npeak during the springtime festival. Then they could be married, and he\ncould live with her in the secret forests high above the village, for she\ncould not leave her home.\nBut Bulan wanted something special for his wedding. He wanted\neveryone to recognize how beautiful and kind his wife was, how blessed\nhe was by her presence. He wanted their celebrations to be grand enough\nfor a dayang.\nThe Mountain traced the lines of unrest pulling at his mouth.\n“What troubles you, my love?” she asked.\nBulan blushed.\n“Ah, Dayang, how I wish I could give you a grand celebration.\nSomething that you deserve. But I do not have the means.”\nThe Mountain knew Bulan would never accept gold from her, but she\nwanted him to be happy, and so . . .\nShe tricked him.\n“Take this,” she said, holding out her hand. “It is a different kind of\ngold, but it will soothe your troubles when you are away from my side.”\nBulan smiled, touched by the gesture. It was nothing more than a\nhandful of ginger root, but it would taste good in stew, and it would spice\nhis mind when he chewed the root. He kissed the Mountain fondly.\n“Starting tomorrow, I will never leave your side,” he whispered,\ntying his bright cloak around him.\nHis eyes brimmed with hope, and the Mountain’s gaze answered his.\nLove was a heady thing, and perhaps if the Mountain was wiser, not so\nfresh in her affections, she might have been more cautious.\nFor, you see, a Mountain is a solitary thing. It owns only a crescent\nof land, the part of itself that arches eagerly to meet the sky. It may look\nat the beings that dance near its skirts, but it sees only the pattern of their\nshapes. It does not see, for instance, the slant of their gaze when one\namong them is continually blessed with catches of fish that look like\nplump jewels, or always empties pockets full of fruit, or always smiles as\nif he is better than all the other villagers.\nWhen Bulan took his leave of his Mountain, he did not secure the\nends of the pouch of ginger. And even as it grew heavier in his pocket,\nhe did not pay it any mind, for soon he was to be married. If he had\nlooked, he would have noticed that it was no longer ginger.\nBut gold.\nTwo men from the village waited for him.\nAt first, they were satisfied. Bulan was not in league with anyone, as\nthey had first suspected. His hands were empty, which was unusual.\nPerhaps there was no reason to be jealous. Perhaps he truly was foraging\nand—as can happen—had found nothing this time. But then they saw the\nglint of gold in his back pocket.\n“Bulan!” they called.\nHe stopped.\n“Where did you get that gold?”\n“What gold?” he replied, confused.\nOne of the men walked up to him, face twisted in a sneer. He ripped\nthe bag of ginger from Bulan, emptying it on the ground. Right before\ntheir eyes, the remaining ginger changed to gold.\n“How?” asked one.\n“Who gave this to you?” demanded another.\nBulan began to panic. The Mountain was his bride. He had to protect\nher from the greed of humans.\n“No one!” he said. “No one gave me anything.”\nOne of the men lit a torch. The other drew a short dagger.\n“We will make you tell us.”\nBulan looked at the moon-gleam on the metal. He knew they were\nright. They would make him tell.\nBut not if he took the chance from them first.\n“Forgive me, Dayang,” he said, reaching for the other man’s knife. “I\nwould rather give my life than force you to yield yourself.”\nAfterward, the men stripped him of his beautiful cloak. They shook it,\nhoping that golden coins would fly loose.\nThey did not notice the small jewel heart thumping silently into the\ndirt.\nThey might have left the clothes with the body, but the night was\ncold, and the cloak was beautiful.\nAnd so. And so.\nThe Mountain wore her wedding dress.\nThere were flowers in her hair. Pearls around her wrists and ankles.\nThe mist threaded through the trees, and clouds of fireflies hovered\nsoftly, so that her world was nothing but sparkling lights and gauzy\ndreams.\nThe sun broke upon her face, and the Mountain could not help but\nthink that the sun had never felt so soft and honey-warm as it did now,\nwhen it shone with the radiance of a hope teetering on being realized, the\nkind of decadent hope that’s about to be snapped between the teeth and\ndevoured whole.\nShe waited.\nShe had made a throne of anemones for Bulan and a crown of\nblossoms where drowsy bees still slept in the folded palm of a flower. He\nwould be amused, she thought, smiling to herself.\nA day passed.\nThen two. Then three.\nThey clotted together, a knot that wouldn’t choke itself down.\nThe Mountain ventured near the slope facing the town. There, she\nsaw Bulan, in the bright orange cloak that he always wore when he made\nhis way to her. The villagers were dancing for their spring festival.\nBulan’s back was to her, but the Mountain still saw the tawny arms of\nanother woman around his neck.\nThe Mountain had never been spurned. Her heartbreak was a thing of\ndistance. Like the pressure of a knife before the pain hits. Black,\nnumbing seconds where a hope—that perhaps there will be no pain—\nflutters just long enough to carve a wound far worse than any knife.\nShe turned her back. Her tears conjured thunderstorms and swelled\nrivers. How cruel that he had stolen her heart. Locked her to this place.\nOn that day, she made a promise: “I will never let another human\nsteal what is mine.”\nPerhaps, if the Mountain had taken two more steps, she would have\nseen it. Her heart glinting dully. Covered in dirt. It had fallen far away\nfrom Bulan’s body, right at the line where the Mountain’s skirts met the\nhuman village. Perhaps, if the Mountain had waited two more moments,\nshe would have seen the man’s face and realized he was not Bulan.\nPerhaps, if the Mountain had not uttered another oath, things might be\ndifferent:\n“I will find my heart, and no one shall steal from me again.”\nPerhaps, perhaps, perhaps.\nAll splinters of a tale.\nThat is why you must not laugh when you see a beautiful woman\nscrabbling at things in the dirt or reaching for high branches.\nThat is why you must turn your clothes inside out.\nThat is why you must empty your pockets of fruit.\nFor the Mountain does not like you to take things that do not belong\nto you.</string>
    <string name="a_filipino_folktale_story">Sometimes a guardian spirit, other times a precolonial goddess, Maria\nMakiling is associated with the Philippine’s beloved Mount Makiling,\nwhose peaks resemble the profile of a young woman. Always\nbreathtakingly beautiful, the reasons for why she stays on the mountain\ndiffer from time period to storyteller. The most popular stories about\nMaria have her stealing away young men to live with her in the forests of\nthe mountain. But her love affairs are not always blissful. In one version\nof the story, told by José Rizal, the Filipino poet and national hero, Maria\nfalls in love with a young man who spurns her love when the army\nbegins to recruit. Instead of waiting for Maria, he marries a mortal\nwoman so that he can safely stay inside his village. Mournfully, she tells\nhim she would have protected him if only he had waited for her. In\nanother tale of Maria, she shows her benevolence by turning ginger into\ngold for a group of villagers. But her benevolence backfires. In some\nversions of the tale, the villagers are grateful and show her love. In\nothers, they become greedy, and break into her mountain garden, hungry\nto see whether all that Maria grows is made of gold.\nMaria is deeply tied to the landscape. People still report sightings of\na woman dressed in white, walking the long mountain road. Sometimes\nshe tries to get a ride down the mountain. As if there were something she\nis trying to outrun.\nI chose this story because no one tale can pin down the personality of\nthis mountain goddess. And yet all stories warn us not to steal from her. I\nwanted to know why. “Forbidden Fruit” is my exploration of her\nbackground and my homage to her presence.</string>
</resources>